<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Traditions | An Off-Topic Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://aylwina.github.io/on//blog/categories/traditions/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://aylwina.github.io/on//"/>
  <updated>2014-12-02T02:27:22-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://aylwina.github.io/on//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aylwin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Traditions]]></title>
    <link href="http://aylwina.github.io/on//blog/2014/12/02/winter-traditions/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-02T02:19:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://aylwina.github.io/on//blog/2014/12/02/winter-traditions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I baked four loaves of fruitcake. In a few days I&rsquo;ll make gluten free apricot fruitcake for my sister, who is far too busy to spend hours prepping dough. My digging out the recipes for Christmas cake is one the first signs of Christmas around here. An even more ominous sign is that a few days ago it snowed, a careful dusting of white over lawns and gardens, one that politely melted off paths and roads. The season is moving forward, days shortening, long, cold nights taking over more and more of life. It will be interesting to see what changes this winter brings.</p>

<p>Winter is a time of sleep for most of nature, a time of transformation, when the seeds of our future rest, waiting for a time when their sprouting will be safe. It seems natural to think of this as the end of the year, but is it fair to call it the start of a new one? Our calendar shows the year ending on December 31st, but this is a date picked almost at random.</p>

<p>If we were to choose a date to begin the new year, what would it be? The earliest recorded celebrations (according to western traditions) used the spring equinox, around the 21st of March. Oddly enough, the Romans started the year in March as well, until Pontillus added two months at the start of the year, instantly messing things up. The evidence of the Emperor&rsquo;s imperial edict mangling our calender is still with us. Ever wondered why October, or eight-ber is the tenth month? Look at the names of the last four months closely and you&rsquo;ll see they are all named after numbers that are two positions out of sequence.</p>

<p>Julius Caesar, as would any military genius, loved simplicity in administration. He threw out the lunar calendar with its weeks that were only usually seven days and lunar cycles that never lined up conveniently with the period of earth&rsquo;s orbit around the sun. His solar based calendar decreed that the new year begins January 1st.</p>

<p>This is an early example of the practical triumphing over the spiritual, leading to loss of knowledge. Always knowing the ebb and flow of the moon&rsquo;s strength, as you do when you have a lunar calendar, is a first step in being able to understand how outside influences like the moon can affect our feelings and behavior. If you doubt the moons effect, visit your local hospital&rsquo;s emergency room on the full moon. You&rsquo;ll see more staff that night than any other; these are practical people who wouldn&rsquo;t be there without cause.</p>

<p>With the collapse of Rome the Church was left preserving what little science was left. In the height of the dark ages, they banned the &lsquo;pagan&rsquo; celebration of January 1st. For centuries they were unable to pick any one date for the new year, various parties arguing for November or Christmas or March until 1582. When the Gregorian calendar was adopted by the Catholic church it officially set New Years as January 1st.</p>

<p>Oddly enough, Protestants felt the new year end an item of faith, one not appropriate for them. America and the British Empire continued celebrating the new year in March until 1752. I can&rsquo;t help wondering, was forcing an obviously foolish new years day on America the straw that broke the camel&rsquo;s back?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
