<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-21T23:32:03-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aylwin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trial and Error]]></title>
    <link href="http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/blog/2014/11/21/trial-and-error/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T12:06:58-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/blog/2014/11/21/trial-and-error</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m hoping this is an acceptable format for another blog. This time I want full control, yet I also want it to be free, since there probably won&rsquo;t be any revenue stream from offering my opinions to the world.</p>

<p>In the process of ending up on github, I&rsquo;ve run into innumerable headaches setting up free accounts using jekyll (this latest with octopress) and github, heroku or openshift. For some reason I didn&rsquo;t even get around to testing Amazon&rsquo;s host, even though they promise to charge only pennies a month on the low level usage I expect. At least I learned something. Several days of struggle made it clear why people pay web hosts for the pleasure of seeing their words online.</p>

<p>The annoying thing is that most of the world uses windows computers, but all the clever dudes setting up the free stuff do it in some flavor of unix. I have a hard time understanding how apple, a reluctant convert to unix and for years a company that preferred hiring lawyers to hiring programmers, has somehow become the favorite of geeks. Using my windows box to attempt to follow apple based unix instructions has proven to be a refined form of mental torture. Sigh.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
