<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[An Off-Topic Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-10T09:57:31-08:00</updated>
  <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aylwin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Derivative of Chaos]]></title>
    <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/12/10/a-derivative-of-chaos/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-10T01:34:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/12/10/a-derivative-of-chaos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most people noticed the recent collapse of oil prices. I watched it in excruciating detail, as I am heavily invested in oil stocks that last month were worth many times what they are today. I held onto them with grim determination throughout their rapid descent, as logic insisted that the price of oil could not fall this far.</p>

<p>I made one of the classic errors of investors. Belief that logic will win out is the enemy of wealth. The market follows emotion, and emotions can be tricked into wanting things injurious to life.</p>

<p>If I am to make that money back, I have to figure out what emotions investors will be feeling over the next few months. Knowing that, I can guess where the market is going and place better bets. I&rsquo;m going to speculate here, hoping to stumble into a useful answer.</p>

<p>The first thing to look at is the irrational beliefs that dominate the market. One of the most irrational is the belief that production of oil has no limits. That is right folks, there is a fixed amount of oil in the ground, and once it is gone, we are done.</p>

<p>Actually, it is worse than that. Oil lurks in &lsquo;traps&rsquo; unless it is heavy oil lying around waiting to leach into the environment. Tight oil, or shale oil, the stuff that has to be fracked, is stuck even more, in stone that is barely porous and hard to get out of. That is why drillers have to shatter the trap under extraordinary pressure, then jam proppants into the cracks to keep them open.</p>

<p>Fracking is weird stuff, using millions of gallons of water along with mystery chemicals that dissolve difficult rocks, or prevent stubborn bacteria or chemical deposits gumming things up. They also use guar gum as a gelling agent to hold proppant in solution (otherwise used as an indigestible food additive.) The most fascinating additives are radioactive tracer isotopes used to determine the location of fractures.</p>

<p>People are horrified when they discover what is being done&mdash;but as usual most miss the real problem. After all that liquid has been injected, the drillers have to get as much as they can back out again before they can get at the oil. At this point the driller has maybe &frac34; of a million gallons of extremely polluted water to dispose of.</p>

<p>Oddly enough, it isn&rsquo;t drilling that causes problems. It is drillers disposing of this toxic waste water into streams or shallow wells that then leach into drinking water. Even when they act sensibly and use dedicated deep wells they can inadvertently lubricate seismic faults and induce small earthquakes. Is it any wonder that citizens are starting to get concerned about having frackers in their neighbourhood?</p>

<p>Fracked wells are also extremely costly. A single well can cost $8 million dollars. The end result (hopefully, given that geologists sometimes guess wrong&hellip;.) is a well that puts out a tremendous amount of oil. At first, anyway. Remember, this is tight oil. The stuff begins to ooze out of fractured rock, but not all the rock is fractured. The fractures may be propped open by sand, but whatever they inject, over a few months the mother rock settles around the proppant.</p>

<p>Within a year, maybe half of the oil that is going to ooze has made its way to the surface. Each month the well produces fewer and fewer barrels a day&mdash;by the time it gets to a trickle &frac34; of the oil may still be locked in the rock. You can throw more and more money at the well to get the remains out faster, but the return on that investment grows less and less. With $40 oil, the well is more likely to be abandoned than stimulated.</p>

<p>This is the source of America&rsquo;s vaunted oil independence. First, its a kind of driller&rsquo;s Ponzi game, where more and more wells have to be drilled just to maintain production, yet the quality of the targets grows less and less. It should be an obvious problem, as no one intentionally drills the least likely site first.</p>

<p>Another challenge is that, oddly enough, fracking is the province of smaller drillers. Big oil was late to the party. Some of these guys are prudent with their money. Most aren&rsquo;t. The problem is that small drillers hoping to grow take out loans they could barely repay at the old prices. They bet the company on the price of oil staying up, not covering their costs by selling next year&rsquo;s oil today. At current prices, many will be broke within a year. Believe me, I&rsquo;m not happy.</p>

<p>Finally, even with drills running day and night, Americans conveniently forget they import 40% of the oil they use. If the price of oil stays down, American oil production could decline by half within two years. That means America will be importing 70% of its oil while saving a ton of money at the pumps. The cost of that oil will be little more than what was paid for less imported oil last year. This won&rsquo;t be all bad, so an investor should try to make money by figuring out long term winners and losers. Right?</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;But this long run is a misleading guide&hellip;. In the long run we are all dead.&rdquo;<br>&mdash;Keynes</p></blockquote>

<p>That seems to capture the investors dilemma. We remember yesterday and imagine tomorrow, but anything beyond that is uncertain. Experienced investors accept they have no clear picture of the future. To balance this, they act as if today is all that matters. When times are good, animal spirits drive markets far beyond their real value. When everyone feels gloomy, prices fall swiftly to irrational lows. The challenge for an astute investor is determining just how irrationally high or low prices will go.</p>

<p>Following the economic meltdown of 2008, the oil price collapsed to around $30 a barrel. With six years of inflation and increased production costs, $40 is the most absurd low anyone can now consider. Can it happen? Logically, no. It would destroy too many companies in the oil industry, taking their investors and banks with them. This disaster would take perhaps a decade to recover from.</p>

<p>In those ten years, the Saudis would (gasp!) be running out of oil. Russia would have been forced into partnership with China to develop their declining fields, and that oil would be contracted to China. America and Europe would be left out. This in itself is dangerous. Japan entered the second world war because America locked them out of oil from Indonesia needed to grow their economy.</p>

<p>Most American tight oil would have declined to stripper mode, yielding a few barrels a day. North Sea oil would be crippled, the Gulf of Mexico and Alaska would both be on their last legs while Canada&rsquo;s oil sands would be struggling to survive.</p>

<p>This would be a triumph for environmentalists, would allow the Saudis to rejoice in crushing Iran, and would let the USA feel they had punished Russia. The real loser, of course, would be anyone wanting to preserve their standard of living. All those bankruptcies in the oil industry would have devastating knock-on effects. The risk is that now the decline in prices has started, external events will ensure it continues down to $40 a barrel.</p>

<p>If this happens, the main cause will be the extraordinary levels of debt dragging down every economy. Addiction to so-called Keynesian economics (more honestly known as buying votes) has led most countries in the world to spend their way out of recession. They have spent so recklessly that they have used up the money needed to support small businesses, the real engines of growth. When the next recession takes hold, most countries will find themselves in a hole without the resources to dig themselves out.</p>

<blockquote><p>It is an extraordinary example of how, starting with a mistake, a remorseless logician can end up in bedlam.<br>&mdash;Keynes</p></blockquote>

<p>The odd thing is that no one can say exactly how and why the oil price decline started. Circumstantial evidence suggests the American government colluded with the Saudi government to trigger the first fire sale, knowing the market would turn it into a rout. With ISIS selling stolen oil to finance their activity, cutting the price they get must have seemed desirable. However, no authority is publicly admitting this goal. The Saudi&rsquo;s publicly say they are doing it to shut down American tight oil. The USA wants us to believe the world is awash in their mite of new oil, and this is a natural market response.</p>

<p>Others point out that futures markets drive oil prices. Futures trade almost ten times the actual volume of oil used every day as contracts for delayed delivery. These largely imaginary deals are supposed to help reveal what the future price of oil will be, and thus preserve capital in the markets. What they do instead is give the trading desks of banks an opportunity to profit from inside information, for hedge funds to put billions into artificially moving markets, and for the little guys, yet another place to gamble on what the market &lsquo;should&rsquo; do, and so lose money.</p>

<p>After carefully considering, the only conclusion I can come to (except that a slow motion disaster is unfolding before us) is that once again, Keynes was right:</p>

<blockquote><p>It is generally agreed that casinos should, in the public interest, be inaccessible and expensive. And perhaps the same is true of Stock Exchanges.</p></blockquote>

<p>But maybe there is one sensible investment hidden in this mess. I could start a sanatorium treating problem gamblers. Just think how much money I could make!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Existential Crisis of Unread Posts]]></title>
    <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/12/08/the-existential-crisis-of-unread-posts/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-08T00:13:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/12/08/the-existential-crisis-of-unread-posts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the classic Zen koans asks &ldquo;if a tree falls in the forest and no one hears, does it make a sound?&rdquo; One&rsquo;s first reaction is to think this a stupid question. Sound is created by the falling tree, so there is no need for an observer.</p>

<p>To the Zen master, there may be sound, or there may not be sound. This depends on sound&rsquo;s reality being nothing but <em>an interpretation by a mind</em> of shock waves generated in the air by the tree. The question is asked of the student to help separate their mind&rsquo;s automatic and completely unnoticed interpretation of the world from the world&rsquo;s underlying reality.</p>

<p>What we believe to be real is our mind dealing with information from our senses. The first understanding of what is real, once we accept our mind and senses can easily create a false reality, is that what is real ought to be what caused our senses to react. But is that the fundamental reality? Following the logic of the koan, we come to realize we are neither the objects of experience nor what we experience. We are the experiencer. Only this is true. As Descartes put it: &ldquo;Cogito, ergo sum.&rdquo; In ordinary English, &ldquo;I think, therefore I am.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Descartes was attempting to find a foundation, a reality that could not be denied. He realized that all sense impressions were not a fundamental truth, just an experience. When we dream, afterwards&mdash;and only afterwards&mdash;we know the experience is false. When we are awake, what proof do we have have of this long drawn out experience being reality, and not just some greater illusion that will be followed by a greater afterwards?</p>

<p>After long consideration, it became clear to Descartes that thoughts contain mere echoes of our sensory experience. Our entire ephemeral reality could be nothing but a dream, but for one simple fact. We exist as the screen of those impressions.</p>

<p>This is the fundamental reality of life. Not the existence of things we crave and collect, deluded by the feeling that owning objects gives self worth. The only true self worth is to experience the experiencer in all its naked grandeur.</p>

<p>As we grow older, the habit of experiencing the world through the senses draws us farther and farther away from our own nature. We become stuck facing out, forgetting there is something inside that allows us to enjoy impressions that come to us from outside our shell of &lsquo;self&rsquo;. To turn our attention back is simplicity itself&mdash;except we have forgotten how.</p>

<p>The koans are there to help us understand the need. Meditation is there to help us redirect our thoughts towards their quiet source within. But even thoughts are not the inner self. The transcendental source of thought is the true goal of meditation. There we find the soul&rsquo;s mirror, an essence that reflects only truth, one that always finds its life&rsquo;s desire. This is something worth having, worth striving for, worth turning upside-down our view of the world.</p>

<p>And yet the thoughts in this blog, which for so long has had no mind other than its creator knowing them&mdash;do they truly exist?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Traditions]]></title>
    <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/12/02/winter-traditions/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-02T02:19:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/12/02/winter-traditions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&ldquo;There are many temptations in this life, but cake is probably one of the biggest of them.&rdquo;
 &mdash;Alexander McCall Smith</p></blockquote>

<p>Today I baked four loaves of a traditional heavy, nutty fruitcake, totally free of those evil maraschino cherries. In a few days I&rsquo;ll make an even healthier gluten free apricot fruitcake for my sister, who is far too busy to spend hours prepping all the fruit.</p>

<p>My digging out the recipes for Christmas cake is one the first signs of Christmas around here. An even more ominous sign is that a few days ago it snowed, a careful dusting of white over lawns and gardens, one that politely melted off paths and roads. The season is moving forward, days shortening, long, cold nights taking over more and more of life. It will be interesting to see what changes this winter brings.</p>

<p>Winter is a time of sleep for most of nature, a time of transformation, when the seeds of our future rest, waiting for a time when their sprouting will be safe. It seems natural to think of this as the end of the year, but is it fair to call it the start of a new one? Our calendar shows the year ending on December 31st, but this is a date picked almost at random.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Time has no divisions to mark its passage, there is never a thunder-storm or blare of trumpets to announce the beginning of a new month or year. Even when a new century begins it is only we mortals who ring bells and fire off pistols.&rdquo; <br>
&mdash;Thomas Mann</p></blockquote>

<p>If we were to choose a date to begin the new year, when would it be? The earliest recorded celebrations (according to western tradition) used the spring equinox, around the 21st of March. The Romans started the year in March as well, until Pontillus added two months at the start of the calendar, instantly messing things up. The evidence of the Emperor&rsquo;s imperial edict mangling our year are still with us. Ever wondered why October, or eight-ber is the tenth month? Look at the names of the last four months closely and you&rsquo;ll see they are all named after numbers that are two positions out of sequence.</p>

<p>Julius Caesar, as would any military genius, loved simplicity in administration. He threw out the lunar calendar with its weeks that were only usually seven days and lunar cycles that never lined up conveniently with the period of earth&rsquo;s orbit around the sun. His solar based calendar decreed that the new year begins January 1st.</p>

<p>This is an early example of the practical triumphing over the spiritual, leading to loss of knowledge. When always aware of the ebb and flow of the moon&rsquo;s strength, as when you follow a lunar calendar, you more easily understand how outside influences like the moon affect our feelings and behavior. If you doubt the moons effect, visit your local hospital&rsquo;s emergency room on the full moon. You&rsquo;ll see more staff that night than any other; these are practical people who wouldn&rsquo;t be there without cause.</p>

<p>After the collapse of Rome the Church preserved what little science they permitted. At the height of their dark ages, they banned the &lsquo;pagan&rsquo; celebration of January 1st. For centuries they were unable to decide on any one date for their new year, various parties arguing for dates in November or Christmas or March until 1582. With the adoption of the Gregorian calendar by the Catholic church New Years became officially January 1st.</p>

<p>The early Church adopted many legends and celebrations from other faiths to enhance the mystique of their own religion. This so confused things that the actual date and location of Christ&rsquo;s birth is unknown. We celebrate Christ&rsquo;s birthday on an old pagan festival for the start of the sun&rsquo;s return. This happens in the last days of what had accidentally became the last month of the year. It is pure luck that the pagan celebration of the sun&rsquo;s revival came so close to the Roman administration&rsquo;s chosen day to start the year.</p>

<p>Oddly enough, Protestants back in the day felt the choice of new year&rsquo;s day an item of faith, one not appropriate for them. America and the British Empire continued celebrating the new year in March until 1752. I can&rsquo;t help wondering&mdash;was forcing an obviously foolish new years day on America the straw that finally broke the camel&rsquo;s back?</p>

<p>An amusing idea, but one obviously untrue. Although unloved for their administration, the Brit&rsquo;s new new year&rsquo;s day was energetically adopted, with the habit of making unreachable resolutions a standard part of the celebration. Ben Franklin summed up the goal of this seasonal desire for self improvement:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Be always at war with your vices, at peace with your neighbors, and let each new year find you a better man.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Siccing the Law on Ferguson]]></title>
    <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/11/27/siccing-the-law-on-ferguson/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-27T09:35:37-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/11/27/siccing-the-law-on-ferguson</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&ldquo;The minute you read something you can&rsquo;t understand, you can almost guarantee it was drawn up by a lawyer.&rdquo; &mdash;Will Rogers</p></blockquote>

<p>The problems in Ferguson have their roots in one simple perception: the law is dangerous. Worse, it seems to deliberately treat the wealthy and whites better than others. Even among those supposedly favoured by the system, the weight of due process routinely crushes the innocent. Our legal system has, over centuries, degenerated into unmanageable complexity. In the process it became dark and dangerous.</p>

<p>Abuse of justice doesn&rsquo;t just grind down people. Bad laws conspire with greedy and indifferent custodians of the law to ruin faith in the American dream. When we no longer share aspirations, the tacit assent to the rules that holds a democracy together starts to fail.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;There is an essential justice which cements society, and one source of the laws establishing justice. That source is logical reasoning. This is the truth that validates all commandments and prohibitions. Whoever neglects this source of laws, whether written or unwritten, is necessarily unjust and wicked.&rdquo; &mdash;Cicero</p></blockquote>

<p>Not all Ferguson&rsquo;s problems come from heavy handed policing. Some irritants are due to laws and lawyers that fail Cicero&rsquo;s test of being logical. Enough people have focussed on the faults of cops in causing Ferguson&rsquo;s problems. Isn&rsquo;t it time other parts of the legal system, those that are themselves unjust, get their moment?</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;All around the world, lawyers generate more hostility than the members of any other profession&hellip;. But there are few places where clients have more grounds for complaint than America.&rdquo;
 &mdash;The Economist</p></blockquote>

<p>One American in 265 works as a lawyer. Doesn&rsquo;t sound so bad, until you realize &frac14; of the population is under twenty (know any kids practising law?) and 1/3 of those working age don&rsquo;t actually work. Heck, when we take out the underemployed and the aged, it becomes even worse. Lets just say that around one percent of the fully employed are lawyers. Now where have we heard that figure before&hellip;.</p>

<p>When the law is simple, the need for lawyers is less. There are now so many conflicting rules and regulations that lawyers live well while litigating cases for years. The vast preponderance of laws seem designed more to enrich the legal profession than to enhance the security of the people.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;The more corrupt the state, the more numerous the laws.&rdquo; &mdash;Tacitus</p></blockquote>

<p>The lawyering up of modern America has been a significant part of the transformation of our economy into one based on renting out rights. Great companies no longer manufacture great products. Instead of relying on heavy industry, renting of technology produces today&rsquo;s wealth. If that doesn&rsquo;t make sense, think about the Microsoft software you use every day, but can no longer own.</p>

<p>Many American oil companies are also raking in the bucks. Their money comes from high-tech as
well. Fracking for shale oil is impossible without 3D seismic, directional drilling, and a whole host of other technologies only geeks can understand. Those companies thrive under high oil prices and may collapse on low. For now, like Jed Clampett, they produce liquid gold, a network of laws letting them &lsquo;rent&rsquo; technology and mineral rights (making lawyers and a few rights owners rich) while needing hardly any workers.</p>

<p>Apple lucked into patentable control of digital music, and from there stumbled into phones. Its intellectual property (IP) portfolio allows it to do little more than litigate away competition while selling at great profit products designed and made by captive foreign manufacturers. This kind of market control easily leads to complacency. Since this has long been one of Apples weaknesses, expect things there to start going downhill. Maybe not this year, but given enough time their role in phones may look a lot like Blackberry&rsquo;s.</p>

<p>Please excuse my grumbling about a company whose products I once loved. The point was supposed to be that Apple&rsquo;s wealth has for years been protected by lawyers. They are the company&rsquo;s great strength. They have helped ensure there is almost no American content in Apple products. They ensure that we can buy and use their branded technology, but we can never earn a penny from making it.</p>

<p>This shift from &lsquo;making things&rsquo; to &lsquo;rent collection&rsquo; is based almost entirely on laws governing IP rights. These laws have been crammed down the throats of every country wishing to trade with the good old USA. It is amusing to look back at the past behaviour of great American companies. Just one example: the founder of Hershey chocolates bragged that he had stolen the secrets of making fine chocolates from the Swiss, using this story to promote his brand.</p>

<p>IP as we now know it exists because it benefits America&rsquo;s leading companies. It isn&rsquo;t clear that it benefits the average person, and especially it doesn&rsquo;t help the developing world. All this modern legal stuff that lets high-tech companies earn high rewards also leads to one obvious problem in America. There are mostly lawyers, techies and salespeople on the inside. Some of those salespeople, like politicians and bankers, are so good they&rsquo;ve convinced us they are experts who&rsquo;s advice we can trust. Sorry, another digression. The point is that we can&rsquo;t even bother applying to any of these positions without a well burnished CV. Ordinary Americans won&rsquo;t get in the door.</p>

<p>Similarly bright lawyers in America&rsquo;s administration have undone structures established over generations to stabilize prices. With the help of brilliant programmers, hedge funds have exploited those markets, making billions by orchestrating, anticipating and encouraging price swings. These exacerbated price swings make business riskier, but they also make the banks running the hedge funds rich.</p>

<p>This leaves us in a position where ordinary jobs are increasingly insecure because of replacement of skilled workers by technology. This process, in turn, has been at least partly driven by surges in commodity prices forcing employers to find ways to save money. Wealth is accumulating around those who take great risks that increase volatility, yet they have a government safety net that prevents losses from the inevitable downswings, as they are &ldquo;too big to fail.&rdquo; Workers, driven to either high skilled or unskilled work, lose badly if they fail the transition. No wonder so many resent the 1%.</p>

<p>Those not making it into the system end up in the service economy. Service jobs, like flipping burgers or washing windows, don&rsquo;t pay well. They also destroy self-esteem. With the average American declining into a kind of second class citizenship, is it any surprise that there is so much hostility towards immigrants? The real problem is that those coming from even worse circumstances are willing to do those brain numbing jobs for less. This makes life even more insecure for marginalized workers.</p>

<p>Ferguson burst into flames after years of widespread grievances over racially biased policing. It is the tip of the iceberg of a far larger problem. With the average Joe unable to get into companies that control the high-tech economy, many more than Ferguson&rsquo;s disenfranchised blacks are annoyed to find themselves among life&rsquo;s losers. Holding no stakes in anyone else&rsquo;s success, unsure where they will be in a few years, some are hoping for some place where they can act out their frustration.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t be surprised if even more people turn up next time something becomes an excuse to light bonfires in the streets. More laws and more police won&rsquo;t prevent it. More discussion in the media will only inflame feelings. What we need instead is for each of us to dedicate a little more time each day to nourishing peace in ourselves. If everyone started doing it, wouldn&rsquo;t that finally bring the change we need?</p>

<p><img src="https://aylwina.github.io/on/images/2014-11-29_122357.jpg" alt="ideal policing" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Failure to Communicate]]></title>
    <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/11/22/a-failure-to-communicate/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-22T12:29:57-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/11/22/a-failure-to-communicate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fewer and fewer people believe they know how to make friends. We obviously have bigger things to worry about, yet this small failing can easily make life miserable. One modern solution is to plead having some flavor of autism, as if this is an all purpose replacement for social competence. I&rsquo;m tempted to do it myself sometimes, but I can assure you it doesn&rsquo;t work. Ignoring people you don&rsquo;t know how to deal with just makes them more irritated.</p>

<p>In our culture of strangers, where we may never talk to our own neighbours, poor social skills are a common problem. Unless we find effective ways to deal with those mysterious &lsquo;others&rsquo;, we&rsquo;ll never make friends, never form new relationships. We&rsquo;ll just be another lost soul, hurrying through life with eyes downcast, unaware of all the fascinating and irritating life around us. Some skill at interacting with those who do fall into our orbit is essential to enjoying life.</p>

<p>The challenges of enjoying other people&rsquo;s company can be thought of in two parts. First we want a way to render disgruntled people we interact with on a daily basis more amiable. Second, we need to find more effective ways to get to know those who are, for some odd reason, predisposed to enjoy being around us.</p>

<p>So what is it that we need to change? For now, I&rsquo;ll stick to the first challenge, getting twits to be more accommodating. My favourite simple instruction is to &ldquo;think good thoughts&rdquo; about the people we deal with. Some people make that particularly hard to do, but with a little luck our positive influence helps them to start thinking better of us&mdash;even while they continue behaving like jerks. Remember, you aren&rsquo;t going to change their nature, just the degree of animosity you have to endure from them.</p>

<p>The heart of this skill is finding something&mdash;<em>anything</em>&mdash;about them to sympathize with. If it doesn&rsquo;t work, complain to Will Rogers. He&rsquo;s the one who claimed: &ldquo;I never met a man I couldn&rsquo;t like.&rdquo; Arriving at equanimity takes effort. You actually have to take time to find out what interests someone, what they might respond to. Rather than listening to gossip, which often has biases, you might actually try asking them. Surely your foe can&rsquo;t be irritating in <em>every</em> aspect of their lives. (In case that doesn&rsquo;t turn out to be true, I can only suggest you flee their influence as far and fast as humanly possible)</p>

<p>A corollary of that instruction is to avoid giving into the temptation to bad-mouth blockheads. Yes, they deserve it, and it does make you feel better. Well, at least temporarily. The problem is that louts <strong>will</strong> hear about your complaints. Usually presented to them in the worst possible light. Keeping your mouth shut with a little luck will fool evil idiots into suspecting you are a better person than you really are. Isn&rsquo;t it better to leave trolls confused rather than becoming all angry and vicious the moment they see you?</p>

<p>We both know that thinking well of others, even when they act foolishly, is not an easy or quick solution. And we by nature prefer easy short term solutions. I can only suggest trying it out, seeing if it will work for you. Since by nature we also resist change, some effort will be involved. The root of resistance to change is the delusion that our opinions are inviolable, that they define who we are. But Kongzi, who oddly enough we call Confucius, told it straight:</p>

<blockquote><p>They must often change opinions who would be constant in happiness or wisdom.</p></blockquote>

<p>However, some people prefer their instructions to be more direct. Hence Lao Tzu at his most succinct:</p>

<blockquote><p>Only when I let go of what I am can I become what I might be.</p></blockquote>

<p>For those who require more detailed instructions he gave them as well:</p>

<blockquote><p>Treat those who are good with goodness, and also treat those who are not good with goodness. Thus goodness is attained. Be honest to those who are honest, and be also honest to those who are not honest. Thus honesty is attained.</p>

<p>Kindness in words creates confidence. Kindness in thinking creates profoundness. Kindness in giving creates love.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trial and Error]]></title>
    <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/11/21/trial-and-error/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T04:06:58-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/11/21/trial-and-error</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have to confess this isn&rsquo;t my first blog. While living in china I tried out a blogging site that I filled with pictures to flesh out bare accounts about my travels. Then microsoft&rsquo;s corporate wizards bought the one I&rsquo;d used, merging it with another. The formatting was altered so much that the bulk of my images looked pathetic. I was lazy about fixing them, which in hindsight was probably a good thing. Soon after, the great firewall of china reared up and blocked the new site completely.</p>

<p>My next effort was part of my own small business website that was supposed to promote the wide range of my developer skills. As you can guess, that cramped my creativity. A lot. There was no way I could rant about trivia on a site promoting dull but reliable web-design efforts. The site cost more than the work it was bringing in (none) so eventually it too was abandoned.</p>

<p>Last month a friend inadvertently convinced me to try blogging again, this time with the hope that I will be consistent enough and interesting enough to have these rambles form the basis of an ebook. Well, actually, she figured I should just sit down and write one. Having tried many times what for me always turns into an unpleasant and unfruitful process, I&rsquo;m instead hoping random spells of creativity will magically coalesce into something interesting. At least this way I&rsquo;ll have <em>some</em> pages presentable. Willing to take any bets on my eventual success?</p>

<p>If it doesn&rsquo;t work that way, I&rsquo;m hoping this site will at least end up an aesthetically acceptable blog. To that end, I want full control, yet I&rsquo;m too cheap to be paying to publish. After all, it doesn&rsquo;t make sense to count on earning big bucks from offering unconventional (yet only occasionally controversial) opinions to the world. Well, at least not these days. The internet is cluttered with so many millions of words supporting so many strange ideas that I can&rsquo;t rationally expect anyone to find this site.</p>

<p>What you find yourself (almost miraculously) reading is starting its life hosted on github. In the process of getting this site up I ran into innumerable headaches. Jekyll (the software running this site) ended up paired with octopress, after abandoning pairings with yeoman and grunt. I was driven back to github after failing to reliably deploy to heroku and openshift. For some reason I didn&rsquo;t even get around to testing amazon&rsquo;s host, even though they promise to charge only pennies a month on the low level usage I expect. At least I learned something. Several days of frustration made it clear why so many people willingly pay for the pleasure of seeing their words looking good online.</p>

<p>To edit each post I now use notepad++, then use a command window to create a temporary local site to see how it looks. When everything works, in another command window I run a rake routine that pushes the new version to github. Easy peasy, eh?</p>

<p>The cause of most of my problems were instructions that didn&rsquo;t work. While most of the world uses windows computers, almost all the clever dudes setting up free stuff do so in some flavour of unix. Windows, based on unix since NT, only with a great deal of persuasion will do full blown unix type things. Using my windows box to attempt to follow apple based unix instructions proved to be a refined form of mental torture. Sigh.</p>

<p>I have a hard time understanding how apple, a reluctant convert to unix and for years a company that filled their halls with lawyers and marketers while treating programmers as expendable, somehow became the favourite of web programming geeks. Well, maybe I should confess I suspect why&mdash;Apple simply didn&rsquo;t have the programming chops to make the flavour of unix they bought run software from their old OS, so the unix they use remains easy to port to. Coding is so much easier when you are willing to blow off the entire powerPC user base.</p>

<p>Since you read this far, you might enjoy a picture from one of the adventures in china that inspired my original blog. Below is a scene from jiuhuashan, or nine flower mountain, a popular buddhist site. The original temple the pond graces was started shortly after the arrival, almost 1300 years ago, of an intensely devoted korean prince. He chose to live in the wilds of china, an area so difficult to reach that even now it is barely touched by development. He spent 75 years living on the mountain as an impoverished but increasingly enlightened buddhist monk. He is said to be still there, sitting in samadhi inside a massive bell sealed under the foundations of the main building. Through much of china he is revered as the incarnation of the god of earth.</p>

<p><img src="https://aylwina.github.io/on/images/Jiuhuashan-pond.jpg" alt="pond in front of Huacheng Temple" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
