<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: New-years-day | A Rambler's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/categories/new-years-day/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-19T11:26:10-08:00</updated>
  <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aylwin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Winter Traditions]]></title>
    <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/12/02/winter-traditions/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-02T02:19:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/12/02/winter-traditions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&ldquo;There are many temptations in this life, but cake is probably one of the biggest of them.&rdquo;
 &mdash;Alexander McCall Smith</p></blockquote>

<p>Today I baked four loaves of a traditional heavy, nutty fruitcake, totally free of the chemical excesses of maraschino cherries. In a few days I&rsquo;ll make an even healthier gluten free apricot fruitcake for my sister, who is far too busy to spend hours prepping all the fruit.</p>

<p>My digging out the recipes for Christmas cake is one the first signs of Christmas around here. An even more ominous sign is that a few days ago it snowed, a careful dusting of white over lawns and gardens, one that politely melted off paths and roads. The season is moving forward, days shortening, long, cold nights taking over more and more of life. It will be interesting to see what changes this winter brings.</p>

<p>Winter is a time of sleep for most of nature, a time of transformation, when the seeds of our future rest, waiting for a time when their sprouting will be safe. It seems natural to think of this as the end of the year, but is it fair to call it the start of a new one? Our calendar shows the year ending on December 31st, but this is a date picked almost at random.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Time has no divisions to mark its passage, there is never a thunder-storm or blare of trumpets to announce the beginning of a new month or year. Even when a new century begins it is only we mortals who ring bells and fire off pistols.&rdquo; <br>
&mdash;Thomas Mann</p></blockquote>

<!--more-->


<p>If we were to choose a date to begin the new year, when would it be? The earliest recorded celebrations (according to western tradition) used the spring equinox, around the 21st of March. The Romans started the year in March as well, until Pontillus added two months at the start of the calendar, instantly messing things up. The evidence of the Emperor&rsquo;s imperial edict mangling our year are still with us. Ever wondered why October, or eight-ber is the tenth month? Look at the names of the last four months closely and you&rsquo;ll see they are all named after numbers that are two positions out of sequence.</p>

<p>Julius Caesar, as would any military genius, loved simplicity in administration. He threw out the lunar calendar with its weeks that were only usually seven days and lunar cycles that never lined up conveniently with the period of earth&rsquo;s orbit around the sun. His solar based calendar decreed that the new year begins January 1st.</p>

<p>This is an early example of the practical triumphing over the spiritual, leading to loss of knowledge. When always aware of the ebb and flow of the moon&rsquo;s strength, as when you follow a lunar calendar, you more easily understand how outside influences like the moon affect our feelings and behavior. If you doubt the moons effect, visit your local hospital&rsquo;s emergency room on the full moon. You&rsquo;ll see more staff that night than any other; these are practical people who wouldn&rsquo;t be there without cause.</p>

<p>After the collapse of Rome the Church preserved what little science they permitted. At the height of their dark ages, they banned the &lsquo;pagan&rsquo; celebration of January 1st. For centuries they were unable to decide on any one date for their new year, various parties arguing for dates in November or Christmas or March until 1582. With the adoption of the Gregorian calendar by the Catholic church New Years became officially January 1st.</p>

<p>The early Church adopted many legends and celebrations from other faiths to enhance the mystique of their own religion. This so confused things that the actual date and location of Christ&rsquo;s birth is unknown. We celebrate Christ&rsquo;s birthday on an old pagan festival for the start of the sun&rsquo;s return. This happens in the last days of what had accidentally became the last month of the year. It is pure luck that the pagan celebration of the sun&rsquo;s revival came so close to the Roman administration&rsquo;s chosen day to start the year.</p>

<p>Oddly enough, Protestants back in the day felt the choice of new year&rsquo;s day an item of faith, one not appropriate for them. America and the British Empire continued celebrating the new year in March until 1752. I can&rsquo;t help wondering&mdash;was forcing an obviously foolish new years day on America the straw that finally broke the camel&rsquo;s back?</p>

<p>An amusing idea, but one obviously untrue. Although unloved for their administration, the Brit&rsquo;s new new year&rsquo;s day was energetically adopted, with the habit of making unreachable resolutions a standard part of the celebration. Ben Franklin summed up the goal of this seasonal desire for self improvement:</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Be always at war with your vices, at peace with your neighbors, and let each new year find you a better man.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
