<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Lawyers | A Rambler&rsquo;s Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/categories/lawyers/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-24T15:25:04-08:00</updated>
  <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aylwin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Siccing the Law on Ferguson]]></title>
    <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/11/27/siccing-the-law-on-ferguson/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-27T09:35:37-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/11/27/siccing-the-law-on-ferguson</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>&ldquo;The minute you read something you can&rsquo;t understand, you can almost guarantee it was drawn up by a lawyer.&rdquo; &mdash;Will Rogers</p></blockquote>




<p>The problems in Ferguson have their roots in one simple perception: the law is dangerous. Worse, it seems to deliberately treat the wealthy and whites better than others. Even among those supposedly favoured by the system, the weight of due process routinely crushes the innocent. Our legal system has, over centuries, degenerated into unmanageable complexity. In the process it became dark and dangerous.</p>




<p>Abuse of justice doesn&rsquo;t just grind down people. Bad laws conspire with greedy and indifferent custodians of the law to ruin faith in the American dream. When we no longer share aspirations, the tacit assent to the rules that holds a democracy together starts to fail.</p>




<blockquote><p>&ldquo;There is an essential justice which cements society, and one source of the laws establishing justice. That source is logical reasoning. This is the truth that validates all commandments and prohibitions. Whoever neglects this source of laws, whether written or unwritten, is necessarily unjust and wicked.&rdquo; &mdash;Cicero</p></blockquote>




<p>Not all Ferguson&rsquo;s problems come from heavy handed policing. Some irritants are due to laws and lawyers that fail Cicero&rsquo;s test of being logical. Enough people have focussed on the faults of cops in causing Ferguson&rsquo;s problems. Isn&rsquo;t it time other parts of the legal system, those that are themselves unjust, get their moment?</p>




<blockquote><p>&ldquo;All around the world, lawyers generate more hostility than the members of any other profession&hellip;. But there are few places where clients have more grounds for complaint than America.&rdquo;
 &mdash;The Economist</p></blockquote>




<!--more-->




<p>One American in 265 works as a lawyer. Doesn&rsquo;t sound so bad, until you realize &frac14; of the population is under twenty (know any kids practising law?) and 1/3 of those working age don&rsquo;t actually work. Heck, when we take out the underemployed and the aged, it becomes even worse. Lets just say that around one percent of the fully employed are lawyers. Now where have we heard that figure before&hellip;.</p>




<p>When the law is simple, the need for lawyers is less. There are now so many conflicting rules and regulations that lawyers live well while litigating cases for years. The vast preponderance of laws seem designed more to enrich the legal profession than to enhance the security of the people.</p>




<blockquote><p>&ldquo;The more corrupt the state, the more numerous the laws.&rdquo; &mdash;Tacitus</p></blockquote>




<p>The lawyering up of modern America has been a significant part of the transformation of our economy into one based on renting out rights. Great companies no longer manufacture great products. Instead of relying on heavy industry, renting of technology produces today&rsquo;s wealth. If that doesn&rsquo;t make sense, think about the Microsoft software you use every day, but can no longer own.</p>




<p>Many American oil companies are also raking in the bucks. Their money comes from high-tech as
well. Fracking for shale oil is impossible without 3D seismic, directional drilling, and a whole host of other technologies only geeks can understand. Those companies thrive under high oil prices and may collapse on low. For now, like Jed Clampett, they produce liquid gold, a network of laws letting them &lsquo;rent&rsquo; technology and mineral rights (making lawyers and a few rights owners rich) while needing hardly any workers.</p>




<p>Apple lucked into patentable control of digital music, and from there stumbled into phones. Its intellectual property (IP) portfolio allows it to do little more than litigate away competition while selling at great profit products designed and made by captive foreign manufacturers. This kind of market control easily leads to complacency. Since this has long been one of Apples weaknesses, expect things there to start going downhill. Maybe not this year, but given enough time their role in phones may look a lot like Blackberry&rsquo;s.</p>




<p>Please excuse my grumbling about a company whose products I once loved. The point was supposed to be that Apple&rsquo;s wealth has for years been protected by lawyers. They are the company&rsquo;s great strength. They have helped ensure there is almost no American content in Apple products. They ensure that we can buy and use their branded technology, but we can never earn a penny from making it.</p>




<p>This shift from &lsquo;making things&rsquo; to &lsquo;rent collection&rsquo; is based almost entirely on laws governing IP rights. These laws have been crammed down the throats of every country wishing to trade with the good old USA. It is amusing to look back at the past behaviour of great American companies. Just one example: the founder of Hershey chocolates bragged that he had stolen the secrets of making fine chocolates from the Swiss, using this story to promote his brand.</p>




<p>IP as we now know it exists because it benefits America&rsquo;s leading companies. It isn&rsquo;t clear that it benefits the average person, and especially it doesn&rsquo;t help the developing world. All this modern legal stuff that lets high-tech companies earn high rewards also leads to one obvious problem in America. There are mostly lawyers, techies and salespeople on the inside. Some of those salespeople, like politicians and bankers, are so good they&rsquo;ve convinced us they are experts who&rsquo;s advice we can trust. Sorry, another digression. The point is that we can&rsquo;t even bother applying to any of these positions without a well burnished CV. Ordinary Americans won&rsquo;t get in the door.</p>




<p>Similarly bright lawyers in America&rsquo;s administration have undone structures established over generations to stabilize prices. With the help of brilliant programmers, hedge funds have exploited those markets, making billions by orchestrating, anticipating and encouraging price swings. These exacerbated price swings make business riskier, but they also make the banks running the hedge funds rich.</p>




<p>This leaves us in a position where ordinary jobs are increasingly insecure because of replacement of skilled workers by technology. This process, in turn, has been at least partly driven by surges in commodity prices forcing employers to find ways to save money. Wealth is accumulating around those who take great risks that increase volatility, yet they have a government safety net that prevents losses from the inevitable downswings, as they are &ldquo;too big to fail.&rdquo; Workers, driven to either high skilled or unskilled work, lose badly if they fail the transition. No wonder so many resent the 1%.</p>




<p>Those not making it into the system end up in the service economy. Service jobs, like flipping burgers or washing windows, don&rsquo;t pay well. They also destroy self-esteem. With the average American declining into a kind of second class citizenship, is it any surprise that there is so much hostility towards immigrants? The real problem is that those coming from even worse circumstances are willing to do those brain numbing jobs for less. This makes life even more insecure for marginalized workers.</p>




<p>Ferguson burst into flames after years of widespread grievances over racially biased policing. It is the tip of the iceberg of a far larger problem. With the average Joe unable to get into companies that control the high-tech economy, many more than Ferguson&rsquo;s disenfranchised blacks are annoyed to find themselves among life&rsquo;s losers. Holding no stakes in anyone else&rsquo;s success, unsure where they will be in a few years, some are hoping for some place where they can act out their frustration.</p>




<p>Don&rsquo;t be surprised if even more people turn up next time something becomes an excuse to light bonfires in the streets. More laws and more police won&rsquo;t prevent it. More discussion in the media will only inflame feelings. What we need instead is for each of us to dedicate a little more time each day to nourishing peace in ourselves. If everyone started doing it, wouldn&rsquo;t that finally bring the change we need?</p>




<p><img src="https://aylwina.github.io/on/images/2014-11-29_122357.jpg" alt="ideal policing" /></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
