<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Free-sites | An Off-Topic Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/blog/categories/free-sites/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-22T12:29:10-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aylwin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trial and Error]]></title>
    <link href="http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/blog/2014/11/21/trial-and-error/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T12:06:58-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/blog/2014/11/21/trial-and-error</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This isn&rsquo;t my first blog. While living in china I used a microsoft site for pictures of rural china to flesh out stories about my trips. Then microsoft&rsquo;s corporate wizards merged that platform with another. My formatting was altered so much that the bulk of my images looked pathetic. I was lazy about fixing them, which was probably a good thing. Soon after, the great firewall of china was created, blocking the site completely from my edits. I happily abandoned it.</p>

<p>My next effort was part of my own small business website that was supposed to promote the wide range of my developer skills. As you can guess, that cramped my creativity. A lot. There was no way I could rant about trivia on a site promoting dull but reliable web-design efforts. The site cost more than the work it was bringing in (none) so eventually it too was abandoned.</p>

<p>A friend convinced me to try blogging again, this time with the hope that I can be consistant enough, and interesting enough to have these rambles form the basis of an ebook. Willing to take any bets on my success?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m hoping this site will end up an at least aesthetically acceptable blog. To that end, I want full control, yet I don&rsquo;t want to be paying to publish. After all, it doesn&rsquo;t make sense to count on a revenue stream from offering unconventional (yet only occasionally controversial) opinions to the world. Well, at least not these days. The internet is cluttered with so many millions of words supporting so many strange ideas that I can&rsquo;t rationally expect anyone to find this site.</p>

<p>What you are reading is currently hosted on github. In the process of getting this site up I ran into innumerable headaches with free accounts using jekyll (the software running this site along with octopress). I was driven here after failing to reliably deploy to heroku and openshift. For some reason I didn&rsquo;t even get around to testing amazon&rsquo;s host, even though they promise to charge only pennies a month on the low level usage I expect. At least I learned something. Several days of frustration made it clear why people are willing to pay for the pleasure of seeing their words online.</p>

<p>The cause of most of my problems were instructions that didn&rsquo;t work. While most of the world uses windows computers, almost all the clever dudes setting up free stuff do it in some flavour of unix. Windows only reluctantly does unix type things. I have a hard time understanding how apple, a reluctant convert to unix and for years a company that filled their halls with lawyers and marketers while treating programmers as expendable, has somehow become the favourite of web programming geeks. Using my windows box to attempt to follow apple based unix instructions proved to be a refined form of mental torture. Sigh.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
