<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sites, | An Off-Topic Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/blog/categories/sites/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-22T10:13:01-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aylwin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trial and Error]]></title>
    <link href="http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/blog/2014/11/21/trial-and-error/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T12:06:58-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://git@heroku.com:stark-anchorage-8425.git/blog/2014/11/21/trial-and-error</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m hoping this will be at least an aesthetically acceptable blog. To that end, I want full control, yet I don&rsquo;t want to be paying to publish. After all, it doesn&rsquo;t make sense to count on a revenue stream from offering unconventional (yet only occasionally controversial) opinions to the world. Well, at least not these days. The internet is cluttered with so many millions of words supporting so many strange ideas that I can&rsquo;t expect anyone to find one more innocuous site.</p>

<p>In the process of ending up on github, I ran into innumerable headaches setting up free accounts using jekyll (the software running this site along with octopress and livereload) and hosted on github after failing to reliably deploy to heroku and openshift. For some reason I didn&rsquo;t even get around to testing amazon&rsquo;s host, even though they promise to charge only pennies a month on the low level usage I expect. At least I learned something. Several days of frustration made it clear why people are willing to pay for the pleasure of seeing their words online.</p>

<p>The annoying thing is that most of the world uses windows computers, but all the clever dudes setting up the free stuff do it in some flavour of unix. I have a hard time understanding how apple, a reluctant convert to unix and for years a company that preferred hiring lawyers and avoided hiring programmers, has somehow become the favourite of web programming geeks. Using my windows box to attempt to follow apple based unix instructions has proven to be a refined form of mental torture. Sigh.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
