<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Autism | A Rambler's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/categories/autism/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-01T17:27:02-08:00</updated>
  <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aylwin]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Failure to Communicate]]></title>
    <link href="https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/11/22/a-failure-to-communicate/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-22T12:29:57-08:00</updated>
    <id>https://aylwina.github.io/on/blog/2014/11/22/a-failure-to-communicate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fewer and fewer people believe they know how to make friends. We obviously have bigger things to worry about, yet this small failing can easily make life miserable. One modern solution is to plead having some flavor of autism, as if this is an all purpose replacement for social competence. I&rsquo;m tempted to do it myself sometimes, but I can assure you it doesn&rsquo;t work. Ignoring people you don&rsquo;t know how to deal with just makes them more irritated.</p>

<p>In our culture of strangers, where we may never talk to our own neighbours, poor social skills are a common problem. Unless we find effective ways to deal with those mysterious &lsquo;others&rsquo;, we&rsquo;ll never make friends, never form new relationships. We&rsquo;ll just be another lost soul, hurrying through life with eyes downcast, unaware of all the fascinating and irritating life around us. Some skill at interacting with those who do fall into our orbit is essential to enjoying life.</p>

<p>The challenges of enjoying other people&rsquo;s company can be thought of in two parts. First we want a way to render disgruntled people we interact with on a daily basis more amiable. Second, we need to find more effective ways to get to know those who are, for some odd reason, predisposed to enjoy being around us.</p>

<p>So what is it that we need to change? For now, I&rsquo;ll stick to the first challenge, getting twits to be more accommodating. My favourite simple instruction is to &ldquo;think good thoughts&rdquo; about the people we deal with. Some people make that particularly hard to do, but with a little luck our positive influence helps them to start thinking better of us&mdash;even while they continue behaving like jerks. Remember, you aren&rsquo;t going to change their nature, just the degree of animosity you have to endure from them.</p>

<p>The heart of this skill is finding something&mdash;<em>anything</em>&mdash;about them to sympathize with. If it doesn&rsquo;t work, complain to Will Rogers. He&rsquo;s the one who claimed: &ldquo;I never met a man I couldn&rsquo;t like.&rdquo; Arriving at equanimity takes effort. You actually have to take time to find out what interests someone, what they might respond to. Rather than listening to gossip, which often has biases, you might actually try asking them. Surely your foe can&rsquo;t be irritating in <em>every</em> aspect of their lives. (In case that doesn&rsquo;t turn out to be true, I can only suggest you flee their influence as far and fast as humanly possible)</p>

<p>A corollary of that instruction is to avoid giving into the temptation to bad-mouth blockheads. Yes, they deserve it, and it does make you feel better. Well, at least temporarily. The problem is that louts <strong>will</strong> hear about your complaints. Usually presented to them in the worst possible light. Keeping your mouth shut with a little luck will fool evil idiots into suspecting you are a better person than you really are. Isn&rsquo;t it better to leave trolls confused rather than becoming all angry and vicious the moment they see you?</p>

<p>We both know that thinking well of others, even when they act foolishly, is not an easy or quick solution. And we by nature prefer easy short term solutions. I can only suggest trying it out, seeing if it will work for you. Since by nature we also resist change, some effort will be involved. The root of resistance to change is the delusion that our opinions are inviolable, that they define who we are. But Kongzi, who oddly enough we call Confucius, told it straight:</p>

<blockquote><p>They must often change opinions who would be constant in happiness or wisdom.</p></blockquote>

<p>However, some people prefer their instructions to be more direct. Hence Lao Tzu at his most succinct:</p>

<blockquote><p>Only when I let go of what I am can I become what I might be.</p></blockquote>

<p>For those who require more detailed instructions he gave them as well:</p>

<blockquote><p>Treat those who are good with goodness, and also treat those who are not good with goodness. Thus goodness is attained. Be honest to those who are honest, and be also honest to those who are not honest. Thus honesty is attained.</p>

<p>Kindness in words creates confidence. Kindness in thinking creates profoundness. Kindness in giving creates love.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
